<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://blog.wedrop.it/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <tabi:metadata xmlns:tabi="https://github.com/welpo/tabi">
        <tabi:base_url>https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.wedrop.it</tabi:base_url>
        <tabi:separator>
            •
        </tabi:separator>
        <tabi:about_feeds>This is a web feed, also known as an Atom feed. Subscribe by copying the URL from the address bar into your newsreader. Visit About Feeds to learn more and get started. It&#x27;s free.</tabi:about_feeds>
        <tabi:visit_the_site>Visit website</tabi:visit_the_site>
        <tabi:recent_posts>Recent posts</tabi:recent_posts>
        <tabi:last_updated_on>Updated on $DATE</tabi:last_updated_on>
        <tabi:default_theme></tabi:default_theme>
        <tabi:post_listing_date>date</tabi:post_listing_date>
        <tabi:current_section>misc</tabi:current_section>
    </tabi:metadata><title>Drop a Blog - misc</title>
        <subtitle>Rants and musings of a software architect</subtitle>
    <link href="https://blog.wedrop.it/tags/misc/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.wedrop.it/tags/misc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.wedrop.it/tags/misc/atom.xml</id><entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Fresh coat of paint, part deux</title>
        <published>2025-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>Sebastian Lauwers</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wedrop.it/blog/fresh-coat-paint-part-deux/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wedrop.it/blog/fresh-coat-paint-part-deux/</id>
        
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nigh on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.wedrop.it&#x2F;blog&#x2F;fresh-coat-of-paint&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a decade ago&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I switched from Pelican to Jekyll as my
blog’s engine. Over the past couple of days, I decided to update the blog engine again with the hope
that it might get me to write (publicly) again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t published in a long time. My last post was written at the request of a friend who asked me
to share a childhood memory. And that was in 2019! I think it’s high time to actually start writing
more things that I can share. Every time I’ve written this kind of post, I’ve promised writing about
technical things. This time around, however, I feel like maybe it’s time for me to release some
different words.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If everything goes to plan, tomorrow should see the arrival of my new keyboard. I decided to dive
into the world of custom mechanical ergonomic split keyboards, and this one only has 36 keys! I’ll
see how long it takes me to write an article using it, and maybe that can be a good motivator in
learning how to type with that keyboard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I’ve noticed that while my typing speed is still quite high (I can still
easily hit 100 wpm), the quality of my typing is decreased massively. I somehow switched to using my
right index to hit the space key, and my right hand is moving &lt;em&gt;all over the place&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in order to hit
many, many keys. As someone who spends many hours on keyboards every day, I’d like to protect myself
from future injuries caused by poor typing hygiene. This mostly happens when I’m using my laptop,
however I’ve started noticing it also when I’m using my full-size keyboard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also decided to cull some old articles. The main reason is that they either said things I
don’t necessarily agree with anymore, or said it in a way that is maybe not as tactful as I would
express those opinions today. As an example, I used to have an article that said I don’t enjoy
managing. But I wrote that article well over a decade ago, and it was mostly during a spat with my
then-manager. And the truth is, I love managing. I love creating and running teams. So why would I
keep words that don’t reflect how I feel today?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        <summary type="html">Culling old writing and modernising tools</summary>
        </entry><entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Fresh coat of paint</title>
        <published>2015-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2015-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>Sebastian Lauwers</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wedrop.it/blog/fresh-coat-of-paint/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wedrop.it/blog/fresh-coat-of-paint/</id>
        
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.wedrop.it&#x2F;blog&#x2F;fresh-coat-of-paint&#x2F;paint-small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paint&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few days, I’ve been thinkering with this blog. Mainly, I got bored of the way it
looked, and just wanted to have something a bit more neutral.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not bashing the way the previous one looked: it had a very definite style that I still very much
enjoy, but it just didn’t quite feel polished enough. I’ve decided to switch blogging engines (I’m
now using Jekyll instead of Pelican), and you can find the new theme information on the about page
if you care. All content, obviously, remains available under a Create Commons license.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also taken this new theme opportunity to pimp things a bit. I’m sure you noticed the massive
cover picture in this article. With the previous design, I prided myself that the page loaded very
quickly, with just a few kb of data. I’ve decided to go for heavier pages, but at least, it looks
and feels more &lt;em&gt;dans l’air du temps&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we’ll be moving soon, and our internet connectivity is bound to be all over the place, I
also relocated the hosting of the blog to one of my servers, instead of the raspberry pi hosted at
home. This should mean better uptime and higher bandwidth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, this server is starting to get quite loaded. Between all the applications and
websites it’s running, I’m starting to feel like a proper webhost :). The only issue is that I do it
for free, most of the time. I might have to start thinking about either getting something beefier,
or moving back to having multiple dedicated servers at the same time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my new job doesn’t really require me to work with servers that much, I kind of feel an urge
to play with mine more. At Interact-IV, I was fixing servers left and right all the time (well,
maybe not all the time, but regularly). At Realm, we don’t have the same kind of hosting business at
all, so unless you count the continuous integration server in the Copenhagen office that falls over
every few days, I really don’t get to exercise my sysadmin skills as much as I used to.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it’s the right time of year to ask me for help setting up your servers :).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        <summary type="html">Over the past few days, I&#x27;ve been thinkering with this blog. Mainly, I got bored
of the way it looked, and just wanted to have something a bit more neutral.</summary>
        </entry>
</feed>
